so thank you for the opportunity here
talk to you and could you tell a little
bit of the story of how you first came
to Ladakh with this film project as a
translator and what you saw there and
how it inspired you to set up your
organization and ended up okay the
answer you only say my name is so it
doesn't matter nor me
okay I first came to Ladakh or little
Tibet as part of a film team as journal
and anthropological son I was a linguist
and I had never heard of this place
called Ladakh which is actually a part
of western Tibet but I was asked to go
long with a documentary film team that
was going to go to this remote area that
had just been opened up to the Western
world and they wanted someone who could
pick up a bit of the language so I
agreed to go along thinking I would be
there for six weeks and then I'd go back
to Paris wells what neither linguist
well I arrived in a part of the world
that had not been colonized and that had
not been developed in other words they
had been affected by the Western world
and I discovered in a high-altitude
desert up at 12,000 feet in Himalayas a
people who were living off very scarce
resources but because there had been
developing for their own lives and had
traded to meet their needs not to supply
a Western market they had a remarkably
high standard of living large beautiful
houses beautiful jewelry and I
discovered more leisure and more
pleasure than we had in the West so I
became fascinated by this culture in
these people I stayed on when the film
was finished and I became fluent in the
language and I over the next few years I
was working on writing down the language
for the first time and I came in contact
with people who I found were also the
happiest people I had ever encountered I
also saw that the area having been
thrown open to the west to tourism and
to change from the outside was being now
developed by the Indian government in
this part
to that lost political to India and I
saw that the development in the
following years created unemployment
which hadn't existed for thousands of
years no one in front of none whatsoever
in creating unemployment in educating
young people for jobs that weren't there
this process also created intense
competition a competition that again
hadn't existed for five hundred years a
thousand years and the cause of that
competition local people started
fighting each other suddenly differences
different groups particularly Buddhists
and Muslims who had lived peacefully
side by side for for five hundred years
were fighting each other so within about
a decade the development process had led
to unemployment and conflict that had
never existed before
at the same time this process was
creating solutions of a kind that had
never existed before so I started
working with the local people to provide
information about the fact that in the
West and around the rest of the world
there were more and more people
questioning this development model and
so my organization Isak for the last
three decades has been trying to raise
awareness around the world in both north
and south about the urgent need to
change the direction of the
away from a fossil fuel-based
centralizing organizing globalizing
economic development or model of
progress towards a more decentralized
localized
ecologically and community-based way of
living so that is what our work is about
and